A Guide to the René Jules Dubos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA122
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Bibliographies, In 2-2½" letter size boxes
  - Bibliographies
    - Bibliographies. Reprint Index, 1926-1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bibliographies. Reprint Index, 1963-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography, 1926-1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Bibliography, 1926-1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Bibliography, 1926-1953 September; 13 pp. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bibliographies. Additions. [Information supplied by Mrs. Jean Dubos, 15 June 1982. Some information incomplete], 1982 June 15 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Dreessen, M. "Preliminary Bibliography". 39 pp (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Bibliographies. Books, Revisions (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Bibliographies. Reprint Index. Miscellaneous pages (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bibliographies. RU Archives Working Copy
    - Bibliographies. RU Archives working copy, 1926-1957; pp 1-26 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies. RU Archives working copy II. pp 27-52, 1957-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Reference Notes
  Reference Note materials are notes taken by RJD on various readings from journals and books.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged as found, according to the date Dubos read the material, not date of publication. Materials in Folders 1-3 and 5-6 were originally bound in untitled looseleaf notebooks.
  - 1971 November-1976 October (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1977 January-December (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1978 January-December (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1979, [originally bound in notebook marked #2]. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1980 January-December (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1981 January-March (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1981, [originally bound in looseleaf notebook #1] (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Reference Notes and Reference Materials
  [Reference materials consist of copies of parts of written works (including correspondence) which Dubos cited in several of his articles and books.].
  - 1964 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1971 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1972 1974-1976 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1973-1977 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1977 1979 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - undated (post 1977?) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Reference Materials, Henriette Noufflard on Halevy (1895), and information on Fontaine, Chesterton and Pasteur, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    In English and French.
- Awards and Honors, circa 1951-1979; 4 folders, 5" letter
  Includes awards, medals, prizes and honorary degrees. Primarily newspaper and magazine clippings. Includes some correspondence and lecture information when receiving an award. Also includes 1973 Nov 4 manuscript of Dubos remarks when accepting the Washburn Award and a list of honorary degrees, 1941-1981 received by R.J. Dubos.
  - 1951 1958 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1963-1964 1968 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1973 1975-1976 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Honorary degrees to René J. Dubos, List of, 1941-1981; Original and carbon copy of (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1966 Arches of Science Award, 4 folders and 4 tapes
    - Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Typescript by D.W. Bronk for Dr. Carl Pfaffmann delivery at Press Luncheon for René J. Dubos announcing Arches of Science Award (Box 9, Folder 5)
      [Dr. Bronk did not attend due to death of Richard Shope].
    - Award pamphlet (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Press release (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Announcement of award, Photocopy (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Tentative Seattle schedule for Dr. and Mrs. Dubos (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1966 October-November (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1967 Aug 8 press release re 1967 award. Dr. Dubos is a member of jury for selection of winner (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Various press releases announcing Dubos winner of 1966 award, 1966 October 4 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Dubos remarks responding to first public announcement of award (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - RU News. Biographical note re Dubos and award, 1966 September (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Printed pamphlet of "Pacific Science Center" (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Congratulatory letters and telegrams with some replies by Dubos, 2 folders
      Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent.
      - A-M (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - N-Z (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Arches of Science Award tapes, 4 tapes (Box 9)
      - Tape 1. Dr. Warren Weaver (recorded abroad for presentation at award ceremony), 1966 September 30
      - Tapes 2, 3, 4. Edward E. Carlson introducing, 1966 October 4; 1 original and 2 duplicates
- Correspondence
  - A - Belle, 5" letter
    - Aa - Ab (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Ac - Ak (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Al (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - American Scholar, 1973-1981 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Am - An (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Ap - Az (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Assises internationales de l'environment, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Bab - Ban (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Barb - Bare (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Bark - Barl (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Barlow, Elizabeth, 1976-1979 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Barn - Barz (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Bas - Bay (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Beam, Alexander, 1976-1980 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Beac - Belle (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Bello - Car, 5" letter
    - Bello - Ben (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Beo - Bin (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Bir - Blum (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Blun - Boh (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Boi - Bol (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Bom - Bot (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Bou - Boy (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Bra - Bri (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Broa - Broq (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Brou - Brow (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Bru - Bul (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Bum - By (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Cab - Cap (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Car (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Cas - Doy, 5" letter
    - Cas - Cav (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Ce (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Cha (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Che - Ci (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Cl - Cm (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Cob - Coh (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Col - Con (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Coo - Cot (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Cou - Coy (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Cr (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Cu (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Da (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - De (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Di (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Doa - Dori (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Dorm - Doy (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Dr - Fy, 5" letter
    - Dr - Dum (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Dun - Dy (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Dubos, René Center, 1976 1978 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Dufresne, Jacques and Hélène, 1976-1982, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Ea - Eb (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Ec - Ei (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Ek - Em (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - En - Er (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Escande, Jean Paul, 1979-1981 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Es - Ey (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Fa (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Fe (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Fi - Fl (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Fo (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Fr (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Fu - Fy (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Gab - Hay, 5" letter
    - Gab - Gan (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Gar - Gay (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Ge (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Gh - Gl (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Goc - Gon (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Goo - Gou (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Gra (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Graham, Laurie, 1978-1980 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Gre (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Gri - Gro (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Gu - Gw (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Haa - Ham (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Han - Harr (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Hart - Hay (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Hea - Kav, 5" letter
    - Hea - Hem (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Hen - Hew (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Hi (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Hob - Hom (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Hoo - Hoy (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Hub - Hunt, D. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Hunt, E. - Hy (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - I (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Ja (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Je - Joh (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Jol - Joy (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Jovanovich, Harcourt Brace, 1973 1977-1980 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Kac - Kam (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Kan - Kav (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Ke - Lo, 5" letter
    - Kea - Ken (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Kep - Key (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Ki (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Kl (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Kn (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Ko (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Kr (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Ku (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Lab - Lang (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Lannes, Sophie, 1977-1981 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Lans - Laz (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Lea - Lee (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Lederberg, Joshua, 1978-1980 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Leg - Ler (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Lev (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Li (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Lo (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Ls - Miles, 5" letter
    - Ls - Ly (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - McA - McC (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - McD - McG (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - McDermott, Walsh, 1972-1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - McH - McK (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - McL - McV (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - McCall, Tom, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Mab - Man (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Map - Mar (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Mankind 2000, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Marois, M., 1974-1981 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Mas - May (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Me (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Mic - Mil (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Miles, Rufus E. Jr., 1975-1981 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Miller - Ornstein, 5" letter
    - Miller, C. Philip, 1970-1981 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Min - Mit (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Moe - Moo (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Mor - Mou (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Morton, James, 1975-1981 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Moyers, Bill Show, 1980-1981 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Mumford, Lewis, 1968-1977 1980-1981 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Mu - My (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Na (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Natural Resources Defense Council (NRDC), Inc., 1974-1981 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Ne (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Noufflard, 1968 1972 1977 1981 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Ng - Ni (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Nk - Nu (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Oa - O'H (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Ornstein, Robert, 1975-1981 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - O'K-Oz (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Paa - Ra, 5" letter
    - Paa - Pap (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Palmer, Arthur, 1979-1982 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Panisset, Maurice, 1962-1966 1970-1971 1976 1978 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Par - Pay (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Pea - Pel (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Pen - Pf (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Ph (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Pi - Pl (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Po (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Pollack, Sheldon, 1976-1981 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Polunin, Nicholas, 1975-1981 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (PNAS), 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Pr - Pu (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Q (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Ra (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Rea - Schm, 5" letter
    - Rea - Reid (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Reil - Rem (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Rh - Ri (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Rob - Roc (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Rogers, David E., 1975-1981 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Rod - Rop (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Ros (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Rot - Roy (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Ru - Ry (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Sab - Sal (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Sam (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - San - Saw (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Scha - Schm (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Schaefer, Karl E., 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Schn - Sobel, 5" letter
    - Schn - Scho (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Schr - Schw (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Sci - Scr (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Scribner's, Charles. Permissions and royalties (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Sea - Sei (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Sel - Sey (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Sha (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - She - Shu (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Sib - Sil (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Sim (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Sin - Siv (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Sk - Sl (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Sma - Smil (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Smith, Mia, 1975-1982 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Smit - Sn (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - So - Sq (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Sobel, David S., 1975-1981 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Sta - Vaux, 5" letter
    - Sta - Sti (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Sto - Sta (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Su - Sz (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Ta (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Te (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - T.E.T.E. - The Eblens (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Th (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Ti (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - To (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Tr (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Ts (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Tu (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Tw (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Ub - Uc (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Ud - Ul (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Un (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Up - Ur (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Vac - VanN (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - VanV - Vau (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Vaux, Kenneth, 1975-1977 1979 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - Ve - Yu, 5" letter
    - Ve - Vu (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Wac - Wan (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Ward, Barbara, 1972 1977 1980-1981 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - War (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Was - Wat (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Wea - Wei (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Wel - Wet (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Wh (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - White, George M., 1977-1981 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Wid - Will (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Wilson (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Win - Wit (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Who - Wol (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Woo - Wy (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Ya (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Ye - Yu (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Young - Zy, Unidentified signature, addresses, Crank letters, Permissions, 2½" letter
    - Young, Larry, 1973-1978 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Za - Ze (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Zi - Zy (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified signatures, addresses (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Crank Letters (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Permissions (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Manuscripts, General and Scientific, 1959-1979
  - Annual Reports 1959-1960, 1960-1961, 1961-1962, 1968-1969, 1969-1970, 1970-1971 and for 1972-1973, 1973-1974, 1974-1975, 1975-1976, 1976-1977, 1977-1978, 1978-1979 lists of publications only, 1959-1979 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Annual Reports 1959-1962, 1968-1971, and for 1972-1979 lists of publications only. In 9-5" letter size boxes.
  - "Address to Undergraduates", 1943 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - "Microbes in the Service of Mankind", 1944 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - "Methods for the Determination of the Antibacterial Activity of Products Containing Tyrothrycin or Gramicidin" (R.J. Dubos and Jean Porter), 1945 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - "Submerged Growth of Small Inocula of Tubercle Bacilli" (R.J. Dubos and Bernard D. Davis), 1945 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Addendum to Submerged Growth of Small Inocula of Tubercle Bacilli" (R.J. Dubos and Bernard D. Davis), 1946 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - "General Review on Tyrothricin and Gramicidin", 1946 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - "Preparation of Fatty Acid-Free Tween 80" (B.D. Davis and R.J. Dubos), 1947 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - "An Enzymatic Method for the Liquefaction of Sputum at Neutral Reaction", 1949 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - "Experimental Work with Tween 80...", 1949 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - re Development of Science and Medicine, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - "Science and the Layman", 1950 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - re Tuberculosis, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - "Attributes of Bacteria that Render them Capable of Causing Disease", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - "Biochemical Factors Controlling Fate of Tubercle Bacilli In Vivo", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - "The Epidemiology of Tuberculosis", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - "Immunity to Tuberculosis", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - "Infection, Illness and Society", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - re Introduction of Dr. A.B. Todd to Harvey Society, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - re Introduction of Barry Wood to Harvey Society, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Frank R. Winton to Harvey Society, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Horace W. Magoun to Harvey Society, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Selman Waksman to New York Academy of Medicine, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - "The Living Earth and Its Microbial Alchemy", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - "Reactions of Host to Presence of Bacteria...", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - "Science and Society", 1951 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - Book Review. "Famine Disease in German Concentration Camps Complications and Sequels..". (P. Helweg-Larson et al), 1952 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - re Chemotherapy of Tuberculosis, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - "Historical and Social Aspects of Tuberculosis", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - "The Influence of Social Factors on Natural Resistance to Tuberculosis", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Carroll Williams to the Harvey Society, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - "Introduction of Dr. Laszlo Zechmeister to the Harvey Society", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Louis Flexner to the Harvey Society, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 33)
  - re Introduction of Dr. Walter H. Seegers to the Harvey Society, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 34)
  - "Microbiology in Fable and Art", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 35)
  - "Presentation of the Eli Lilly Award to Dr. J. Oliver Lampen", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 36)
  - "Presidential Message" S.A.B. Newsletter, 1952 April (Box 25, Folder 37)
  - "Tubercle Bacilli and Their Poisons", 1952 (Box 25, Folder 38)
  - "Social and Biological Aspects of Tuberculosis", 1953 (Box 25, Folder 39)
  - "Antituberculosis Immunity Induced in Mice by Vaccination with Killed Tubercle Bacilli..." (D.W. Weiss and R.J. Dubos), 1954 (Box 25, Folder 40)
  - Book Review: "A History of Medicine". (Ralph H. Major), 1954 (Box 25, Folder 41)
  - "The Germ Theory Revisited", 1954 (Box 25, Folder 42)
  - "Reduction of Ferric to Ferrous Ion as an Index of Metabolism", 1954 (Box 25, Folder 43)
  - "Reduction of Tetrazolium as an Index of Metabolism", 1954 (Box 25, Folder 44)
  - "Environmental Determinants of Tuberculosis", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - "Longevity, Health and Infection", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - "On Living at Peace with Infection", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - "Survival and Healty Through Adaptation to the Environment", 1956 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - "The Unknown of Staphylococcal Infection", 1956 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - "Infection into Disease", circa 1956 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - "Address at Schick Testimonial Dinner", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - "The Evolution and Ecology of Tuberculosis", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - "Protein Intake and Resistance to Infection", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - "Science and the Cell", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - "Tuberculosis in Human History", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - "Limitations Inherent in Chemotherapy of Tuberculosis", circa 1957 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - "Medical Progress and Social Goals", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - "Nutrition, Emotion and Infection", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - "The Production of Immunity to Tuberculosis by Fractions Derived from Killed Tubercle Bacilli", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - "Tulipomania and the Benevolent Virus", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - "Tulipomania and the Concept of Disease", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - re Environmental influence on disease, circa 1958 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - "Ars Medica", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - re Environment and disease, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - "External Environment and Susceptibility to Infection", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - "The Infinitely Small: Microorganisms in Human Life and in Science", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - "In Flight NY - Rio; In Rio; In Flight from Rio via Dakar on to Paris", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - "Medicine as a Social Science", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - "Post Prandial Musings on Resistance to Infectious Diseases", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - re RU Convocation Presentation of Hon. Doct. to Gherardo Forni, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - "The Scientist as Philosopher", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - Book Review: "The Life of Sir Alexander Fleming." (André Maurois), circa 1959 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Untitled. "Homer Smith - Illustrates that science implies a faith...", circa 1950s (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - "Adaptability for Survival and Growth", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - "Expectancy", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - "Integrative and Creative Aspects of Infection", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - "Louis Pasteur", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - "Science and Conscience in Modern Medicine", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - "Should We Attempt Eradication of Tuberculosis", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - "Two Cultures", 1960 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - "Beyond Traditional Medicine", circa 1960 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - "Levels of Understanding and Kinds of Observations", 1961 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - "Portraits of the Mind" Lecture 1. Salmon Memorial Lectures, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - "The Adaptive Potentialities of Man" Lecture 2. Salmon Memorial Lectures, circa 1962 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - re Environmental ethics, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - "Life on Earth", 1965 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - "Experimental Medicine Revisited: Claude Bernard After 100 Years", 1968 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - "Moon Landing", 1969 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - "Science for Man", 1969 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Book Review: "The Evolution of Man and Society" (C.D. Darlington), 1970 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - "Genetic Constitution and Environmental Conditioning", 1970 (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - "Science of Social Design". Introduction to "Science Looks at Itself", 1970 (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - "Mabel Bright" 25th year at RU, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - "Of Human Diversity", circa 1970s (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Preface. "The Relevant Earth" (D. Leveson), 1971 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - "Environment in its Relation to the Progress of Bacterial Invasion in TB...", 1972 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - "Improving on Nature", 1972 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to "From the Land and Back". (Curtis Stadtfeld), 1972 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - "Lewis Mumford. National Medal for Literature", 1972 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Foreword to "Pasteur: The History of a Mind." (Emil Duclaux), 1973 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - "From Nature to Resources...", 1973 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - "Introduction of Maurice Strong as F. Osborn Memorial Lecturer", 1973 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - on living in cities, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - "Sensory Perception and the Museum Experience", 1973 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Foreword to "Concepts in Ethology: Animal and Human Behavior." (Michael Fox), 1974 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - "Man Adapting to Working Conditions", 1974 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - "Pasteur's Dilemma - The Road not Taken", 1974 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - "This is the Place - A Man-Made Place", 1974 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - "The Assets of Diversity", 1975 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - re Ecological philosophy, 1975 (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - "The Future of Infectious Diseases", 1975 (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - "Living History", 1975 (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - "St. John the Divine - Lent", 1975 (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - "Scientific Knowledge and Social Wisdom", 1975 (Box 28, Folder 20)
  - "Controlling Pathological Processes", 1976 (Box 28, Folder 21)
  - "Creative Adaptations to the Future", 1976 (Box 28, Folder 22)
  - "Symbiosis Between the Earth and Humankind", 1976 (Box 28, Folder 23)
  - "Controlling Pathological Processes...", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 24)
  - "Environmental Design...", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 25)
  - "Environment, Social Choices and Human Development", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 26)
  - "Genetic Engineering — An Acceptable Risk", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 27)
  - "Naturae Vis Medicatrix", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 28)
  - Preface to "Vocabulaire de l'Environment" (Paul Brace, Editor and Translator), 1977 (Box 28, Folder 29)
  - "Remarks at Gateway Citizens Committee Foundation Briefing", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - "Shelters, Open Spaces and Adaptations", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 31)
  - "This is the Place - A Man-Made Place", 1977 (Box 28, Folder 32)
  - "The Environmental Forum and the Greening of Energy", circa 1977 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - "The New Frontiers in American Society", circa 1977 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - "The Willed Future", circa 1977 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - "The Art of Living", 1978 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - "The Built Environments of the Machine Age", 1978 (Box 29, Folder 5)